Collis Potter Huntington Papers
Collis Potter Huntington Papers
The 1870s witness the expansion of Huntington's roads, particularly the Chesapeake and Ohio and the Southern Pacific. The officers of the various roads report their monthly earnings, and comment on problems in both construction of new roads and upkeep of completed roads due to weather, accident, or an occasional robbery. They also lament the lack of qualified locomotive engineers, conductors, and motive power. Manufacturers of railroad materials, rails, iron, lumber, locomotives and rolling stock, solicited business from Huntington's lines, while producers of foodstuffs and dry goods sought preferential rates.
Donations were sought by a number of groups such as colleges, missionary societies and the like. Few of these people received money from Huntington though a notable exception was the Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute in Hampton, Virginia. Huntington was always sympathetic to the lot of blacks in the United States and favored education as the way to self-sufficiency. Huntington built a sawmill for the Institute and annually donated scholarships. The letters of Samuel C. Armstrong, principle of the Hampton Institute, testify to the aid Huntington gave. Huntington later helped Booker T. Washington, a Hampton Institute graduate himself, to establish Tuskegee Institute in Alabama.
In 1872 the Credit Mobilier scandal is a topic of discussion. So too is the Contract and Finance Company which was the Central Pacific's counterpart of the Union Pacific's Credit Mobilier Company. The railroad owned the construction company to which it awarded inflated contracts thereby pocketing huge profits and at public expense as it was government money. The railroad, in effect, created its own middle man which it could then control. Charles F. Crocker was the middleman for the Contract and Finance Company.
The opening of the transcontinental railroad put a crimp in the profits of those steamship companies who transported goods from the Orient around the Cape. The Pacific Mail Steamship Company, which was partially owned by stock speculator and manipulator Jay Gould, in 1874 refused to send goods by way of the railroads. Huntington countered by forming his own steamship line to feed Asiatic goods to the Central Pacific.
Realizing he would need the cooperation of Gould, who owned the Union Pacific, Huntington formed the Occidental and Oriental Steamship Company with Gould. Shortly thereafter the Pacific Mail Steamship Company began again to ship goods by rail.
Huntington's lang range plan to build a transcontinental railroad wholly owned by himself was in part influenced by a desire to avoid problems, such as the above with Gould. The Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad was planned as the eastern end of such a road. Monthly reports on the progress and earnings of the Chesapeake and Ohio are found in the correspondence. There are also references to the building of Huntington, West Virginia, which Huntington intended as the western terminus of the Chesapeake and Ohio. In expanding the Chesapeake and Ohio westward Huntington bought out financially troubled railroads, the first of which was the Elizabethtown, Lexington and Big Sandy Railroad. The correspondence of John Echols and attorney William Breckinridge detail both the construction and legal problems surrounding the Elizabethtown, Lexington and Big Sandy Railroad, where virtually any sizable town in Kentucky through which it passed started a legal battle over the right of way.
There appears in the incoming correspondence personal letters to Huntington from friends and relatives, though not in any volume. Beginning in 1876 and continuing on and off through 1893 there are letters from Mrs. Anna Judah, widow of surveying engineer Theodore Judah. Judah became involved with California railroads in 1854 when he surveyed a route for the Sacramento Valley Railroad and later surveyed a route for the San Francisco and Sacramento Railroad. Judah also acted as a Lobbyist for the latter road trying to entice prospective stockholders and advocating Federal aid to build intra-state feeder lines which would insure traffic for the proposed transcontinental railroad. In 1859, Judah helped organize a statewide convention on the building of the Pacific Railroad, which then sent him to Congress to lobby for the transcontinental.
Supporters of the railroad in California were divided over which route the transcontinental should follow. The route would determine the terminus of the road, in effect determing what area of California would reap financial benefits. In 1860, Judah set about to form his own railroad company and among the prospective stockholders in Sacramento was Collis P. Huntington, by this time a well-to-do and respected businessman. Judah sought money to complete the survey of the line and lay enough track to satisfy the federal subsidy provisions. After much discussion Huntington and Mark Hopkins each invested $1500 and took Judah in as an equal partner.
By June of 1861 the associates of the Central Pacific Railroad Company filed articles of incorporation with the secretary of state of California. Leland Stanford, soon to be governor of California, was elected president; Huntington, vice-president; Judah, chief engineer; and Mark Hopkins, treasurer. Judah surveyed the line and lobbyed in Congress. When the associates subscribed to the Central Pacific stock they did so on the margin system. In 1863, Huntington called for additional funds from the stockholders in order to complete enough track to get federal money. Judah sold his interest in the company to Charles F. Crocker for $10,000, while retaining an open option to buy further shares. In November 1863, Judah and his wife Anna sailed for New York to raise money. Theodore contracted tropical fever while crossing through Panama and died shortly after his arrival in New York.
Anna Judah always feit it was her husband's efforts which allowed Huntington and his associates to build the transcontinental railroad which made them all very wealthy men and said so in her letter to Huntington. Apparently Anna would write numerous appeals after which Huntington would advance her money usually as a mortgage on some of her property.
Among the correspondents of the 1870s is Huntington's nephew, Henry Edward Huntington. Though Henry would later become an officer of the Southern Pacific Railroad and marry his uncle's widow, only his early correspondence is represented in this series. Henry's early letters ask his Uncle Collis for money to start a business. While inspecting the Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad, Huntington purchased a saw mill in St. Albans, West Virginia, and put Henry in charge in partnership with Richard Franchot, chief congressional lobbyist for the Central Pacific. After returning to the family business in Oneonta, New York, for a few years, Henry reappears as an engineer on the western extension of the Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad.
Lobbyist Franchot, formerly a Congressman from Schenectady, New York, who had served on the House Select Committee on the Pacific Railroad, kept Huntington informed of Congressional actions regarding railroads.
John Boyd was another of Huntington's congressional "look outs" on Congress whose official title in 1875 was "Ass't Doorkeeper in the Capitol Building." Boyd and Franchot sent reports to Huntington concerning the various bills before Congress affecting his railroads. By these reports Huntington knew who his friends were in Congress and also whom he should try to influence. John Boyd often sent newspaper clippings relevant to Huntington's interests. When Richard Franchot died in 1876, Charles Sherrill took his position with the official title "Advisor and Agent of the Central Pacific Railroad in the City of Washington before Congress and the Departments."
David D. Colton joined the associates in 1873 and was soon made president of the Rocky Mountain Coal and Iron Company of Wyoming. By mid-1874, Huntington realized Colton's talents and sent him to Washington to work as a lobbyist for the Southern Pacific. There are many of Colton's letters in this series; they cover the period from 1873 to his death in 1878.
Beginning in the 1870s and continuing to the end of the correspondence are letters calling for interest payments on Central Pacific bonds, as well as the bonds of Huntington's other roads. Some came from large investment houses such as Speyer & Co. in Germany who held millions of dollars of bonds in Huntington's railroads. Other calls for interest payments came from banks, both large and small, law firms seeking redress for their clients, and private investors. There are a few letters from Congressmen asking Huntingtn's advice on what stocks and bonds would be safe purchases.
The letters of Charles F. Crocker and Mark Hopkins testify to the problem of raising cash to pay both interest on the bonds and to continue construction on new lines. Congress early realized that if railroads had difficulty paying interest on their bonds they would also have difficulty paying their debts to the government. Congress passed the Thurman Act which created a sinking fund to which the railroads would contribute out of their net earnings to repay government loans. The Thurman Act is a topic of discussion in the letters of Boyd and Sherrill in 1878.
A man of Huntington's position, head of an expanding railroad empire, could command an influence in both national and local politics. For example, in 1878, when Samuel Axtell and T.B. Catron, respectively governor and U.S. attorney for the Territory of New Mexico, are threatened with removal they write to Huntington and ask him to use his influence to protect their jobs.
As mentioned above, Huntington had as one of his aims the construction of a transcontinental rail system wholly owned by himself. Thomas Scott, president of the Pennsylvania Railroad, had the same goal. In 1868 Scott met with Huntington and told him of his plan to build a transcontinental railroad along a southerly route terminating in the proposed Southern Pacific Railroad, which at that time was only a paper road. Scott offered to buy out Huntington's interest with a small piece of Scott's proposed construction company (the Central Pacific was not yet completed). Huntington begged off and completed his own negotiations for the Southern Pacific. Scott's next attempt at his own transcontinental system came in 1870 with the Texas Pacific Railroad Bill which is discussed in the correspondence. The bill would allow Scott to build new roads and buy up old ones and gave him a virtual monopoly on Texas roads.
1880s
The 1880s see the further expansion of Huntington's railroads. Details leading to Huntington gaining a controlling interest in the Galveston, Harrisburg, and San Antonio Railroad can be found in the correspondence, particularly in the letters of Thomas Peirce, president of the Galveston, Harrisburg, and San Antonio Railroad. Control of this line gave Huntington the foothold he needed in Texas (for which the Southern Pacific had no charter to build), and effectively stopped the Texas and Pacific which was now owned by Jay Gould.
By this time in the correspondence there are a myriad of letterheads for Huntington's railroads and construction companies. The construction companies were set up along the same lines as the now defunct Contract and Finance Company (which had been dissolved in 1873). The Pacific Improvement Company was Huntington's construction company for the Southern Development Company in New Mexico. The Chesapeake and Ohio's construction firm was the Contracting and Building Company, which built the Maysville and Big Sandy extension of the Chesapeake and Ohio. Details leading to the takeover of the Maysville and Big Sandy Railroad can be found in the correspondence. The problems of buying land and obtaining rights of waycontinued in Kentucky.
The development of Newport News begins in this period. Huntington planned Newport News as both a harbor terminus of the Chesapeake and Ohio and as a ship building and dry dock center. As with the railroads there soon began monthly progress reports and then monthly earnings reports. There is also correspondence dealing with the building of the Southern Pacific Railroad in Arizona and New Mexico.
In 1882, Boyd and Sherrillreported an a bill to limit Chinese immigration. This bill was of importance to Huntington as it would limit his supply of cheap labor to build his railroads. The lobbyists also report on congressional action to forfeit land grants to the railroads on which proposed lines had not yet begun. Huntington also received letters and flyers from inventors and distributors of new safety gear, such as air brakes, improved car couplers, railroad crossing gates, and even a patented passenger car spittoon. Mrs. David D. Colton brought suit against the Central Pacific in 1882. When her husband joined the associates he was offered twenty thousand shares in both the Central and Southern Pacific Railroads in return for which he signed a note for one million dollars which would fall due in October 1879. After Colton's death in 1878, bookkeepers discovered that Colton had misappropriated company funds in anticipation of his inability to pay the million dollar note. Huntington, Stanford, and Crocker told Mrs. Colton they would cancel the note if she turned over the securities that her husband held in their companies. They assured her this was a fair bargain as the securities were not worth a million dollars. She then agreed. When Mrs. Colton read newspaper accounts of the value of the estate of Mark Hopkins she believed she had been swindled and brought suit. While she ultimately lost her case she gave much ammunition to Huntington's detractors by reading many of Huntington's letters to her husband into the court record. The letters gave accounts of money Huntington paid to Congressmen, as well as his efforts to manipulate legislation. Letters concerning Mrs. Colton's case are numerous.
Evidence of philanthropy on Huntington's part are scant. As mentioned above, Huntington donated money to the Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute in Alabama. There is also correspondence from Booker T. Washington of Tuskegee Institute. Apparently Huntington also gave money to the Pacific Theological Seminary in California, and there are letters that indicate donations to the Metropolitan Opera Company in New York. L. di Cesnola of the Metropolitan Museum of Art sought and received a number of donations to obtain desired individual items or collections for the museum.
The election of Leland Stanford to the U.S. Senate in 1885 put a wedge between Stanford and Huntington that was never fully removed. Huntington had supported his long-time friend and political associate Aaron A. Sargent for the Senate seat and had even persuaded Stanford and Sargent to bury their lang standing feud. When the California electorate returned a Republican majority to the state legislature, Huntington fully expected that Stanford would support Sargent. Instead Stanford ran for the seat and was elected. Huntington feit betrayed and relations between the two were never quite the Same.
Charles Sherrill died in 1887, and John Boyd took over as chief congressional lobbyist. Among the topics discussed in his correspondence of the late 1880s were a proposed investigation of the Pacific railroads by Congress, and the Interstate Commerce Commission's efforts to regulate the railroads.
Inquiries about the interest payments due an bonds of Huntington's companies continue from the New York, Brussels, and Frankfort offices of Speyer and Company. Huntington travelled to Europe in 1887 in an effort to pacify European bondholders whose main complaints were late interest payments and annual company reports which were not quite so annual or accurate. Huntington wrote many letters to his secretary Isaac Edwin Gates while he was in Europe and these appear in this series.
1890s
In the 1890s Huntington became involved with railroads in Africa. Huntington had lang been sympathetic to the plight of blacks in the United States and was a fervent supporter of the earlier anti-slavery movement. He invested in railroads in Africa (the Congo Railroad and the British East Africa Company) because he feit that the railroad would bring civilization to Equitorial Africa and thereby help to end the slave trade. Huntington's involvement with the anti-slavery movement can be followed in the letters of Francis W. Fox and Sir William Mackinnon.
The correspondence for this decade presents the situation that while Huntington made the avowed aim of taking politics out of the railroads he became more and more involved in politics particularly in California. The letters of William Mills show how Huntington manipulated public opinion by purchasing newspapers and attempting to influence others; this at a time when there was much anti-railroad feeling in California. Mills' letters give a day-to-day account of California politics.
Lobbyist Boyd kept Huntington informed of the actions of the Congressional investigations of the railroads. In 1893, Huntington was called to testify before the committee, yet there is little mention of this in the correspondence. Among the topics that occupied the correspondence during the 1890s was the Panic of 1893. Its effects in California are detailed in the letters of William Mills; banks closed, money was tight, and interest payments were due. The associates turned to Stanford for assistance, but he died and his estate was tied up in probate. The question of the free coinage of silver is discussed with William M. Stewart, U.S. Senator from Nevada. The Pullman Strike of 1894 is discussed in letters from Mills. The strike had little effect in California, but it did muck to feed anti-railroad feelings there. Agitation in California against the railroads is mentioned in the correspondence, while in Congress debate continued over a Funding Bill by which the railroads would repay their debts to the government.
The correspondence of the latter part of the 1890s deals mainly with the day-to-day business of running an enormous railroad and steamship empire. One of the last additions to this empire was the Raquette Lake Railway, which allowed Huntington to visit his retreat in the Adirondacks.
By the time of his death on August 13, 1900, Huntington had an interest in the following companies of which this is by no means a complete list:
Chesapeake & Ohio Railway Company
Galveston, Harrisburg, and San Antonio Railway Company
Guatemala Central Railroad Company
Louisiana & Western Railroad Company
Maysville and Big Sandy Railroad Company
Mexican International Railroad Company
Newport News and Mississippi Valley Company (another holding company)
Newport News Shipbuilding & Dry Dock Company
Occidental and Oriental Steamship Company
Old Dominion Land Company
Old Dominion Steamship Company
Oregon & California Railroad Company
Pacific Improvement Company
Pacific Mail Steamship Company
Raquette Lake Railroad Company
Southern Development Company
Southern Pacific Coast Railway Company
Southern Pacific Company (a holding company the associates formed in 1884)
United States and Brazil Steamship Company
Western Union Telegraph Company
The incoming correspondence ends with letters of condolence to Issac Edwin Gates from friends and business associates on the death of his friend and employer.
Other Formats Available
The entire collection is also available on microfilm, both at Syracuse University and at numerous other academic institutions across the country.
Arrangement of the Collection
See Scope and content above. Note that Boxes 199-218 no longer exist; their contents have been transferred to phase boxes (Oversize packages 1-24).
Related Material
A microfilm version of the Collis P. Huntington Papers (Microfilm #5022) is available.
See also the following:
Anna Hyatt Huntington Papers
Arabella Huntington Papers
Archer Milton Huntington Papers
Huntington Estate Papers
Subject and Genre Headings
Railroads; Business and Industry; Ames, Oakes, 1804-1873.; Anthony, Susan B. (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906.; Armstrong, S. C. (Samuel Chapman), 1839-1893.; Axtell, Samuel B. (Samuel Beach), 1819-1891.; Blaine, James Gillespie, 1830-1893.; Bonn, William B.; Boruck, Marcus D. (Marcus Derckheim), 1833 or 4-1895.; Boyd, John.; Cesnola, Luigi Palma di, 1832-1904.; Chandler, William E. (William Eaton), 1835-1917.; Colton, David Douty, 1832-1878.; Conness, John.; Crocker, Charles F.; Crocker, Charles, 1822-1888.; Crocker, E. B. (Edwin Bryant), 1818-1875.; Echols, John.; Flagg, John Henry, 1843-1911.; Fox, Francis W.; Franchot, Richard.; Gates, Isaac Edwin.; Gilman, F. N.; Gorham, George Congdon, 1832-1909.; Gould, Jay, 1836-1892.; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885.; Hopkins, Mark, 1813-1878.; Huntington, Collis Potter, 1821-1900 Archives.; Judah, Anna Pierce, 1828-1895.; Miller, Edwin H.; Mills, William H.; Prince, L. Bradford (Le Baron Bradford), 1840-1922.; Sargent, A. A. (Aaron Augustus), 1827-1887.; Sherrill, Charles H.; Stanford, Jane Lathrop, 1828-1905.; Stanford, Leland, 1824-1893.; Stewart, William M. (William Morris), 1827-1909.; Storrs, James.; Strong, William B.; Towne, Alban Nelson, 1829-; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915.; Wickham, Williams Carter, 1820-1888.; Williams, George Washington, 1849-1891.; Woodward, J. H.; Central Pacific Railroad Company.; Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad Company.; Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute (Va.); Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company.; Southern Pacific Railroad Company.; United States., Interstate Commerce Commission.; California, History, 1850-1950.; Capitalists and financiers, United States.; Ciphers.; Entrepreneurship.; Palaces -- United States.; Philanthropists -- United States.; Railroad law -- United States.; Railroads -- California.; Railroads -- History.; Railroads -- Freight -- Rates.; Railroads -- United States.; Railroads and state -- United States.; Upper class -- United States.; United States -- History -- 1865-1898.; United States -- Politics and government -- 19th century.; United States -- Social life and customs -- 19th century.; Account books.; Bills of sale.; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Daybooks.; Deeds.; Ledgers (account books); Letterpress copybooks.; Maps (documents); Mortgages.; Photographs.; Receipts (financial records); Stock certificates.; Capitalists and financiers.; Entrepreneurs.; Philanthropists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Anna Hyatt Huntington.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1856 (Box 1)
  - 1863 (Box 1)
  - 1864 (Box 1)
  - 1865 (Box 1)
  - Jan 1866 (Box 1)
  - Feb 1866 (Box 1)
  - Mar 1866 (Box 1)
  - May 1866 (Box 1)
  - Jun 1866 (Box 1)
  - Jul 1866 (Box 1)
  - Sep 1866 (Box 1)
  - Dec 1866 (Box 1)
  - Jan 1867, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Feb 1-25 1867, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Mar 1867 (Box 1)
  - Apr 1867, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - May 1-27 1867, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - June 1-28 1867, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - July 1867 (Box 1)
  - Aug 1867 (Box 1)
  - Sep 1867 (Box 1)
  - Oct 1867 (Box 1)
  - Nov 1867 (Box 1)
  - Dec 1867, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Jan 1868 (Box 1)
  - Feb 1868 (Box 1)
  - Mar 1868 (Box 1)
  - Apr 1868 (Box 2)
  - May 1868 (Box 2)
  - June 1868 (Box 2)
  - July 1868 (Box 2)
  - Aug 1868 (Box 2)
  - Sep 1868 (Box 2)
  - Oct 1868 (Box 2)
  - Nov 1868 (Box 2)
  - Dec 1868 (Box 2)
  - Jan 1869 (Box 2)
  - Feb 1869 (Box 2)
  - Mar 1869 (Box 2)
  - Apr 1869 (Box 2)
  - May 1869, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - June 1869, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - July 1-14 1869 (Box 2)